{"tossups": [{"question": "A memorial to honor soldiers killed while serving on these vessels was built by the War Graves Commission. The first time these weapons were used in World War One resulted in the sinking of the HMS<em> Pathfinder</em>. One of these vessels under the command of Iron Cross winner Otto Weddigen [[VEH-dih-gehn]] sank the so-called \"Live Bait Squadron\" in a single hour. For ten points, identify these naval submarines operated by the German Empire during the First and Second World Wars.", "answer": "<b><u>U-Boat</u></b>s (accept <b><u>U-Boot</u></b>s; or <b><u>Unterseeboot</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "While in Paris, this man met with scientists Michel-Eugene Chevreul [[shev-RUHL]] and Ogdon Rood, who inspired his theories on the \"language of color.\" This developer of chromo-luminarism depicted the raucous Moulin Rouge [[moo-LAHN ROOZH]] in<em> The</em> <em>Can-Can</em>, and he was rejected from the Paris Salon after completing the massive<em> Bathers at</em> <em>Asni\u00e8res[/a] [[ahz-NYEHR]]. For ten points, name this French advocate of pointillism, on</em> <em>display in his [i]A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte</em> [[ZHAHT]].", "answer": "Georges Pierre <b><u>Seurat</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The year after this disaster, Thomas Edison produced the short film<em> The Cost of</em> <em>Carelessness</em>. This disaster was worsened by the fact that Max Blanck and Isaac Harris, who owned the factory at which this event took place, locked the doors to prevent unauthorized breaks. The American Society of Safety Professionals was founded in the wake of this industrial disaster. For ten points, name this 1911 fire which killed hundreds of garment workers in New York City.", "answer": "<b><u>Triangle Shirtwaist</u></b> Factory Fire", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The case<em> Tinker v. Des Moines</em> concerned wearing an armband within these institutions to protest the Vietnam War. Horace Mann promoted a series of reforms concerning these institutions that included gradual secularization and professionalization. The Race to the Top and No Child Left Behind programs affected these institutions.<em> Brown v.</em> <em>Board of Education</em> mandated desegregation within, for ten points, what institutions in which children learn?", "answer": "<b><u>School</u></b>s (accept Public or Private <b><u>School</u></b>s; accept Common <b><u>School</u></b> Movement; accept Elementary, Middle, or High <b><u>School</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Education</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {}, {"question": "Josephus [[joh-SEE-fus]] claimed this monarch led a futile thirteen-year siege of Tyre [[\"TIRE\"]], later coming to terms with its king, Ithobaal III [[ith-oh-BALE \"the third\"]]. This restorer of the Ishtar Gate supposedly blinded the king of Judah, Zedekiah, for rebelling against his rule. In the biblical tradition, this Chaldean [[kahl-DEE-un]] king cast Shadrach [[SHAD-rak]], Meshach [[MEE-shak]], and Abednego [[ah-BED-neh-go]] into the fiery furnace and had his dreams interpreted by Daniel. For ten points, name this long-reigning king of the Neo-Babylonian Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Nebuchadnezzar</u></b> [[neh-buh-kahd-NEH-zar]] II (or <b><u>Nab\u00fb-kudurri-u</u><u>\u1e63</u><u>ur</u></b>; accept <b><u>Nebuchadnezzar</u></b> the Great)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In this city's Congress of Peace, it was determined that the Holy See should have its sovereignty revoked. The League of Nations headquarters was moved from London to this neutral city in 1920, remaining so until the League's dissolution. French reformer John Calvin led a semi-theocratic government in this city during the 16th century. A convention that regulates the rules of war is named for, for ten points, what Swiss city?", "answer": "<b><u>Geneva</u></b> (accept <b><u>Gen\u00e8ve</u></b>; or <b><u>Genf</u></b>; or <b><u>Ginevra</u></b>) (8) While head of the Provisional Theatre, Bed\u0159ich Smetana [[BED-ur-zhik SMEH-tah-nah]] returned this composer's first draft of the historical comedy<em> King and</em> <em>Charcoal Burner</em> after declaring it unperformable. His time in Iowa among fellow Central Europeans led to this composer writing the<em> American Quartet</em>. African-American spirituals influenced this man's composition,<em> Symphony from the New World</em>. Bohemian folk music often inspired, for ten points, which Czech composer's<em> Slavonic Dances</em>? ANSWER: Anton\u00edn <b><u>Dvo</u><u>\u0159</u><u>\u00e1k</u></b> [[deh-VOR-zhak]] (or Anton\u00edn Leopold <b><u>Dvo</u><u>\u0159</u><u>\u00e1k</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man credits his relative lack of injury during his playing career to training in <em>aikido</em> with actor Bruce Lee. This basketball player participated in the \"Game of the Century\" under coach John Wooden, being held to 15 points, in part due to a scratched cornea. This athlete, who pioneered the \"Skyhook\" technique, boycotted the 1968 Olympic Games shortly after his conversion to Islam. For ten points, name this Milwaukee Bucks and Los Angeles Lakers legend, a Hall of Fame Center.", "answer": "Kareem <b><u>Abdul-Jabbar</u></b> (accept Ferdinand Lewis \"Lew\" <b><u>Alcindor</u></b>, Jr.)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The only known source of the Safaitic [[sah-fah-IH-tik]] language is from this kind of art piece. There are several ancient Roman examples of this art form found in Pompeii, often accompanied by lewd jokes. The use of stencils for this art form developed in France in the 1980s. Commercialized by artists such as Banksy, for ten points, what generally unsanctioned art typically takes the form of writing or drawing on a wall or some other surface?", "answer": "<b><u>Graffiti</u></b> (or <b><u>Graffito</u></b>; prompt on \"Street Art\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "After this judge was elected head of his country's supreme court, he rapidly succeeded the conservative Ignacio Comonfort [[koh-mohn-FOR]] as president. This man led the liberals during the War of the Reform and asserted himself as the legitimate president after the French Intervention installed Emperor Maximilian in Mexico City. For ten points, name this first indigenous president of Mexico, whose name graces a city that shares a border with El Paso, Texas.", "answer": "Benito <b><u>Ju\u00e1rez</u></b> [[HWAH-ress]] (or Benito Pablo <b><u>Ju\u00e1rez</u></b> Garc\u00eda)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man's seminal work<em> Syntactic Structures</em> elaborated on his teacher Zellig Harris's generative grammar theory and became a foundational text of cognitive science.", "answer": "Noam <b><u>Chomsky</u></b> (or Avram Noam <b><u>Chomsky</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {"question": "The<em> Castro v. Superior Court</em> decision inspired one of these people, Oscar Acosta, to write<em> Revolt of the Cockroach People</em>. Boxer and poet Rodolfo Gonzales led the \"Crusade for Justice,\" which agitated for the cultural development of these people. The Delano Grape Strike of the 1960s was led by a man of this ethnicity who popularized the phrase \"Si, Se Puede\" [[see-seh-PWEH-deh]]. Labor leader Cesar Chavez was from, for ten points, which Hispanic minority in the U.S.?", "answer": "<b><u>Mexican</u></b>-American (accept <b><u>Chicano</u></b>s; prompt on \"Latine,\" \"Latino,\" \"Latinx,\" or \"Hispanic\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Governor William Berkeley created a bicameral legislature made up of this body and the Council of the State. Shortly before being dissolved by Lord Dunmore, Patrick Henry told this body to \"Give me liberty or give me death.\" This legislative entity was first established in 1619 in Jamestown and later moved to Williamsburg. For ten points, name this legislative body of Colonial Virginia.", "answer": "House of <b><u>Burgesses</u></b> (prompt on \"(First or Second) Virginia Convention(s)\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The White Army-aligned Alasha Orda controlled this modern nation's area for three years before surrendering to the USSR. The Soviet Space Program launched the<em> Vostok</em> missions from this country's Baikonur [[BYE-koh-noor]] Cosmodrome. The Russian-led Commonwealth of Independent States was established by an agreement signed in this nation known as the Almaty Protocol. Nursultan Nazarbayev [[nah-zar-BYE-eff]] once ruled, for ten points, what former Soviet republic in Central Asia?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Kazakh</u></b>stan (or <b><u>Qazaq</u></b>stan Respublikasy; accept <b><u>Kazakh</u></b> Soviet Socialist Republic; or <b><u>Qazaq</u></b> Ke\u0144estik Sos\u0131al\u0131stik)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The critical success of Giacomo Meyerbeer's [[MY-ah-BEH-yuhs]] work<em> Le proph\u00e8te</em> [[luh-proh-FET]] led this former benefactor of his to publish the anti-Semitic treatise <em>Jewishness in Music</em>. King Ludwig of Bavaria brought this composer to Munich, and under his patronage he premiered the opera<em> Tristan und Isolde</em>. For ten points, name this 19th-century German composer who created the mythologically-inspired<em> Ring</em> cycle.", "answer": "Richard <b><u>Wagner</u></b> [[REE-kard VAHG-nuh]] (or Wilhelm Richard <b><u>Wagner</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A 1980 film made about this case is entitled [its plaintiff's]</u></b><em><b><u> Trumpet</u></b></em><b><u>. This case</u> <u>selectively incorporated the Sixth (+)</u> Amendment across the United States. The plaintiff in this case, who had robbed a Florida pool hall, was not granted counsel due to having only committed a felony, as opposed to a capital (*)</b> offense. For ten points, name this 1963 Supreme Court decision that established the legal right to counsel for defendants who are unable to afford their own attorneys.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Gideon</u></b> v. Wainwright</em> (or<em> Clarence E.</em> <em><b><u>Gideon</u></b> v. Louie L. Wainwright, Corrections</em> <em>Director</em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A boldly polyphonic opera named for this character was originally performed</u> <u>at the 1607 Carnival for the court in Mantua and is the earliest still-performed opera</u> <u>of Monteverdi. (+)</u> A lampoon of this character's story by Jacques Offenbach [[OH-fen-bahk]] includes the \"Galop Infernal,\" a song later adapted to the can-can dance, and is titled for [this character]</b><em><b> in the Underworld</b></em><b>. (*)</b> For ten points, name this musically-gifted Greek hero, whose love for Eurydice [[yoo-RIH-dih-see]] is the subject of many operas.", "answer": "<b><u>Orpheus</u></b> [[OHR-fee-us]] (accept<em> L'<b><u>Orfeo</u></b></em>; accept <em><b><u>Orpheus</u></b> in the Underworld</em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>While serving under this man, a young P. G. T. Beauregard provided vital</u> <u>reconnaissance during the Battle of Cerro Gordo. Shortly before his death, this man</u> <u>formulated the Anaconda (+)</u> Plan as a way to cut-off the Confederacy from naval trade. The amphibious seizure of Veracruz by this man facilitated his march on Mexico (*)</b> City during the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this one-time Whig presidential candidate and general known as \"Old Fuss 'n' Feathers.\"", "answer": "Winfield <b><u>Scott</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Using the codename</u></b><em><b><u> Bolek</u></b></em><b><u>, this man likely informed on his fellow workingmen</u> <u>regarding dissident matters such as listening to Radio Free Europe. This electrician</u> <u>led a strike of (+)</u> 17,000 workers at the Lenin Shipyards in Gdansk [[guh-DANSK]]. This man achieved semi-free elections following the Round Table Agreements held in Warsaw. The leader of the trade union (*)</b> Solidarity was, for ten points, what first president of a democratic Poland?", "answer": "Lech <b><u>Wa</u><u>\u0142\u0119</u><u>sa</u></b> [[LEK vah-WEHN-sah]] (be lenient on pronunciation)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>The oldest still existing one of these instruments is named for Charles IX [[the</u> <u>ninth]] of France, who first mass-ordered them from Italy for his court musicians. The</u> <u>search for the most accomplished virtuoso of this instrument is held yearly during the</u> <u>(+)</u></b> <em><b>Premio Paganini</b></em><b> in Genoa. One of these instruments named</b><em><b> Soil</b></em><b>, which is in the possession of Itzhak [[EET-zahk]] (*)</b> Perlman, was created by the accomplished luthier Antonio Stradivari [[strah-dih-VAH-ree]]. For ten points, name this stringed instrument which is smaller than a viola.", "answer": "<b><u>Violin</u></b> (accept the <b><u>Fiddle</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This location was first discovered by a European when Portuguese explorer</u> <u>Vicente Pegado went searching for gold between the Zambezi and Limpopo rivers.</u> <u>This African (+)</u> citadel likely served as the western terminus of a trade route that reached the Swahili Coast and extended to medieval China. The Shona (*)</b> people built, for the point, what ancient city which shares its name with a southern African nation governed from Harare [huh-RAH-reh]]?", "answer": "Great <b><u>Zimbabwe</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>While under the engineer Lucius Cornelius Balbus, this man led the artillery</u> <u>corps during Caesar's Gallic campaign. This man innovated the technology of the</u> </b><em><b><u>hypocaust</u></b></em><b><u> [[HY-poh-kost]], which provided central (+)</u> heating to villas and baths. This polymath stated that all buildings should have \"Utility, Strength, and Beauty\" in his multi-volume work</b><em><b> De Architectura</b></em><b> [[ar-kee-tek-TOO-rah]]. Leonardo (*)</b> Da Vinci drew a figure of a \"Man\" named for, for ten points, which ancient Roman architect?", "answer": "Marcus <b><u>Vitruvius</u></b> Pollio (accept the <b><u>Vitruvian</u></b> Man)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This publisher of the newspaper</u></b><em><b><u> L'Ami du peuple</u></b></em><b><u> [[lah-MEE-doo-poo-PUHL]]</u> <u>lived in the Paris sewers until the seizure of the Tuileries [[twee-leh-REE]] Palace and</u> <u>capture of (+)</u> Louis XVI [[\"the sixteenth\"]]. For his role in organizing the September Massacres, this Jacobin [[JAK-oh-bin]] was assassinated by Girondin-supporter Charlotte (*)</b> Corday. For ten points, name this French Revolutionary figure who is depicted dying in a bathtub in a Jacques-Louis David [[dah-VEED]] painting.", "answer": "Jean-Paul <b><u>Marat</u></b> [[mar-RAH]] (be lenient on pronunciation)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In this year, student demonstrations during the Mexico City Olympics led to a</u> <u>bloody reprisal by Mexican armed forces in the Tlatelolco [[TLAH-teh-LOHL-koh]]</u> <u>Massacre. The Tet (+)</u> Offensive ended in September of this year, and protests in this year at the Chicago Democratic National Convention included heated confrontations between police and Vietnam (*)</b> War protestors. For ten points, name this year, the first U.S. presidential election victory for Richard Nixon.", "answer": "<b><u>1968</u></b> (accept <b><u>1968</u></b> Summer Olympics; accept <b><u>1968</u></b> Democratic National Convention; accept <b><u>1968</u></b> United States Presidential Election)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}